Can everybody hear me?
>> Yes.
Right. We'll
>> wait till we have 100 students and
Okay, just a few more seconds.
All right, let's begin. So uh
what was the last topic we covered last
C
the last major topic we covered CNN's
right so far we've looked at what neural
networks are we've looked at how to
train neural networks then we looked at
convolutional neural networks now we are
moving on to our next series of topics
which is recurrent neural networks and
this is the first lecture in the series
So rec neural networks are used to when
we need to model series. There are many
situations where you need to consider an
entire series of inputs to produce an
output and the output two may be a
series. For example, speech recognition.
Let's say you wanted to look at a
recording and say determine if this
recording includes the word hello.
Then you'd have to analyze the entire
recording to make sure that hello was
spoken just to ensure that the person
didn't simply say hello and and stop or
say something else. Right? So the input
is a sequence of vectors, spectral
vectors and the output is a single
classification result. This is a simple
case. Here's something more challenging.
This is something that every Steelers
fan including me encounters every
season. The Steelers, meanwhile,
continue to struggle to make stops on
defense. They have allowed on average 30
points a game and have shown no signs of
improving anytime soon.
Is there any clue in this
uh passage about the game?
What game is being played? Is it
cricket? Is it baseball? Is it
basketball? Is it football? What is it?
Anyone? Football. Okay. How did you know
that it's football?
So,
Steelers.
Well, there are lots of teams called
Steelers and not all of them play
football, right? So, what about the rest
of it? What else did you know take from
this?
Struggling to make stops on defense.
Allowing 30 points a game. Allowing 30
points a game is not a bad thing if it's
basketball, right? Uh and so, uh no
signs of improving anytime soon. That's
a that that's that's a semantic that's
attached to the Steelers for the longest
time. So, you actually had to analyze
the entire sequence of words before you
realize that this was talking about
football and not basketball, right? Uh
right anytime soon. And uh similarly, if
you're analyzing documents and if you
want to identify the topic, you have to
read the entire document. Or if you want
to translate an English sentence into
French, it's the sequence of words that
matters, not just the fact that there
are a bunch of words. Well, here's
something that I will use more
frequently in today's uh lecture.
Analyzing the stock market. So, every
day you get a vector which is the value
of stock indices, stock prices for a
collection of stocks. This changes day
from day to day and you would like to
analyze the sequence to determine on any
given day whether you it's worthwhile
investing in a specific stock or not. So
again the decision must be taken
considering how things have fared over
time. So these are classification and
prediction problems where the input is a
sequence of vectors. It's not a single
vector. It's not a collection of
vectors. It's the nature of the
sequence. Is there an increasing trend?
Is there a decreasing trend? What is the
nature of the sequence? That's what's
telling you that and giving you the
information, right? Or in this case, if
I jumble up the words, the meaning is
going to be very different. The
sequentiality is is is important. So
these are all problems where the input
is a sequence and the output can be one
or more values or or a sequence itself.
And clearly if
an I have an input and I have an output
there's a function in between this can
be modeled by a neural network.
Before I continue
uh let's uh let's let me just introduce
a uh notation
representation your standard pictorial
representation. Now your standard neural
network has many layers. Each layers has
many units. The input would have many
components. uh the subsequent layers
would have many neurons and so on. If I
turn this network on the side and if you
look at this picture from the side, this
is what it's going to look like. So this
box here represents this entire sequence
of this entire array of values. This box
here represents this entire
layer of neurons and so on. So uh I'm
going to show because of the nature of
the problem that we have and the kind of
illustrations we will need. I'm always
going to show the network sideways like
this. So for example, if I had a net of
this kind which looked at two
consecutive vectors before uh before
producing its output. If I show it from
the side, it's going to look like this
picture to the right. or a network of
this kind where the second vector is
first passed through its own hidden
layer before it's merged with the first.
This network when drawn from the side is
going to look like this. So if you see a
picture of this kind, you must
immediately assume that each box over
here actually represents an entire layer
going into the page. And so when I when
you have an arrow over here, the most
generic assumption is that every neuron
in this layer is connected to every
neuron in this layer. Is this
illustration clear to everybody?
Right? This clear to everyone? I see
one. All right? Can I see a few? Okay.
All right. So that's what we're going to
use. Okay.
Let's go back to the stock market
problem. We have to consider a series of
stock values in the past. And if you
want to decide if you whether you must
invest in a specific stock or not, you
want to see the trend. So you must
consider the series of stock values in
the past several days to decide if it is
wise to invest today.
What kind of model would look at past
values to make a prediction? Now
something that you've already
encountered
a TDN, right? Something like this. I
have a new network. It looks at the
current input and a bunch of past
inputs. You did this in homework one.
And so on each day, it makes a
prediction based on that day's stock
values and the stock values from the
past few days.
So this is just a convolutional network,
a TDNM, right?
And this accounts for history. But is
this sufficient?
Would this be sufficient? Say you're
dealing with a stock market. Is it
sufficient to look at the past four
days? No. What would you want to look
at?
You'd want to look at many many more
days. Right? This is a finite response
system. Something that happens today
only affects the output of the system
for n days into the future. N is the
width of the system. So here for
example, n is four, right? Consider
something that happened on this day
shown by the orange square. So that is
going to influence the prediction on the
same day. It's going to influence the
prediction on the next day and the next
day and the next day for four days and
then afterwards it stops influencing the
predictions. So an input influences the
output for only a finite amount of time.
So this is a finite response system.
This notion of a finite response system
clear to everybody.
Okay. And obviously four days is not
enough, right? you want to look at uh
more time if you're looking at the stock
market. So to consider more of the past
to make predictions you must increase
the history considered by the system you
could do so by simply increasing the
number of inputs it considers.
Well, this increases the number of
parameters.
That a problem? Not really. We have the
CPU. We have the memory. So, we we might
imagine that we can do it. But the
reality is there's no finite window
which is sufficient to give you an idea.
Here is a uh view of the stock market of
one of a uh spy stock called spy I think
over a year. And you can see the trends
and you're going to see weekly trends
because some people get, you know,
people buy things on weekends and they
don't go to the market on Wednesdays
more often than not. So if you looked at
the past seven days, you're going to get
a better idea of what is going to happen
today. But then there are monthly trends
because people get paid at the end of
the month and so then immediately after
they get paid things uh you know the
economic activity increases for a brief
while but then you have seasonal trends
because if you ever go to the department
store you're going to see that things
change season to season to season right
uh the stuff you get in autumn is very
different from the stuff you get in in
in in winter which is very different
from what you get in spring which is
very very different from what you get in
summer. So, you're going to have to go
back and look for the past several
seasons. You have to look at the last
summer, but then you also have to look
at how the other seasons change to see
if there's an overall change in the in
in the economic uh state of the nation
of the world. And so, whether you're
going to expect the same thing as last
summer or something more, you have to
look over a much longer period of time.
But then you have annual trends. Things
shoot up every Thanksgiving. It's not
enough for you to look at just one
Thanksgiving. You'd have to look at
several Thanksgivings to know the
trends. So, this means that something
like this is not going to do, right?
You're going to have to look back over
all infinite time. So, what we need is
an infinite response system where what
happens today continues to affect the
output forever, possibly with weaker and
weaker influence.
So you want something of this kind where
the output on any day depends not just
on the input on that day but all the
inputs going back to the very beginning
of time. Is this problem statement clear
to everybody? Yes or no?
Okay. This is what we're going to be
dealing with. Okay. So here is your
first
hole.
15 seconds, guys.
Let me stop this. Okay. What is the
answer to the first question?
True or false? True and false. First
one's true and the second is false.
Okay, let's see. Convolutional networks,
neural networks and finite response
systems, right? And an input at time t
affects the output of the convolution
layers. It doesn't affect it for all
time because it's a finite response
system. What we need is an infinite
response system. So how can we construct
an infinite response system? Here's a
very simple way of doing it. I can say
that the output at any time depends on
the input at that time but also the
output at the previous time. So yt is a
function of yt minus one. Now consider
what happens to a network of this kind
when you give it an input x0 at time z
and then you produce give it no further
inputs. If you give it no further inputs
the input at time z is going to produce
y0. Thereafter this input is zero. But
then at at time one you have y0. So y0
is going to produce y1. Then y1 goes in
here. Y1 produces y2. And so on and so
on and so on. So you're going to
continue to produce outputs all the way
to y infinity even though you got only
one input at time zero. So a single
input influences the output for the rest
of time. This is an infinite response
system. And in this particular case,
because it's the output being fed right
back in, it's what is called a kn
network. Kn stands for nonlinear auto
reggressive network with exogenous
inputs. And here
the information about what has happened
in the past is being carried by the
output of the network at each time. So
did this not notion of how this is an
infinite response system make sense to
you guys?
Right? And so how does this work? Like
so right at any time you get the XT, you
produce the output YT. At the next time
you take the next input, but then this
YT goes in and produces the next Y. And
then at the next time that Y goes in
along with the next input and produces
the next Y and so on. So this is the
computation being performed. Right? So
no this any odd input sequence would
work. Right? So it's it's just how we
are adding information about the past
through the output. That's the answer to
vimman. So this is the entire sequence
of comput computations being performed
at each time you consider the current
input and the past output to produce the
current output.
So let me simplify this because the
yellow thing is not really a neuron.
It's it's an actual value. So I can
rewrite like this where the final output
layer produces the output at any time
and its output also gets fed into the
next time. This is just a simplification
of this picture. And then you can see
how if I produce an give give it an
input at any time
this keeps influencing outputs for the
rest of time. And so a single input at
time t=0 is going to produce outputs all
the way to t= n infinity forever.
This make sense to all of you guys
over here? Okay. And so this is a simple
one where at each time you're only
considering the current input and the
immediate past output. You can
generalize it and say I'm going to
consider several P current and several
past inputs and the immediate past and
several past outputs. And this is a more
generic uh not network but it still
carries the same principle that history
what happened in the past is dragged in
primarily through the output of the
network which carries this memory and is
fed back into the network.
That make sense?
Yes.
Okay. So, NS networks were very popular
for the longest time. They were very
good for very popular for time series
predictions used to they were used to
predict weather. Stock market markets.
All the hedge funds and all the uh
investment banks had various versions of
Knox networks to predict the stock
markets. Uh they were used as an
alternate system model and tracking
systems. They were used to model
language. Any phenomenon with a distinct
innovation that drives an output meaning
the output has its own trend and then
you have an input that keeps modifying
it that could be modeled using a KNX
network. The key thing over here is that
the memory of the past lies in the
output of the network. What can the
drawback be with this
anybody? What can the drawback be with
this structure where the memory lies
entirely in the output?
Loss of information. Okay, Alex,
explain.
That's a good answer. Explain.
So, let me answer. Right. Typically, how
large is this output?
If you're making a prediction, maybe
it's a vector that you're predicting,
right? Maybe you're predicting a
10-dimensional vector. So you have this
10 component vector over here which is
supposed to carry information about
everything that happened in the past.
But the network itself is much larger
within the network. It computes to in
order to compute these 10 values. The
network has likely computed thousands or
tens of thousands or millions of
intermediate values all of which have
been used to compute this guy. So the
real information about the past is not
just this. This thing has summarized the
whole thing into a very small number of
values. The actual information about
what all the thought processes of the
network lie here. That make sense?
Yes or no?
Right. And so
a and so here we have right this guy is
not sufficient. So let's try to make the
memory more explicit so that the memory
captures more of the internal thought
processes of the network.
To do this we're going to use introduce
a explicit memory variable whose job in
life is to remember. It has no other job
but to remember. And so the memory at
any time is a function of the latest
output. The hidden values in the
immediate past maybe and the past memory
and the hidden values at any time are
dependent on the input and what's in the
memory and the output depends only on
the hidden values. So now we have used
this guy to keep keep track of
everything that has happened in the
past. Now this looks a little complex
and there were a few different variants
of
on how to implement it. The first was
the Jordan network. In the Jordan
network, this memory unit simply
maintained a running average of all past
outputs. Now, in the in the standard KNS
network, you only considered the latest
past output or you explicitly considered
a bunch of past outputs. If you want to
consider all past outputs, then what's
the simplest way of considering all past
outputs? to maintain a running average
and use the average of all past outputs
as your memory value. Right? And so the
Jordan network introduced this memory
element whose job in life was to
maintain a running average of all past
outputs. And you can see how it did so.
The current value was always mu * the
past value plus 1 * the latest value.
And this was what fed into the uh into
the rec into the computation at the next
time. This make sense the Jordan
network.
Okay. Now the question is does this
network actually satisfy our
requirements?
The idea that we started with what was
the idea we started with?
So what was the idea we started with
when he said you know we said the output
is not enough. Correct? The output is
summarizing things too much. You want to
remember what happened inside the
network. Correct?
And this has not solved the problem.
Maybe it remembers a little more, but it
still suffers from information loss.
What's happening inside the network is
still hidden. So the next thing that
comes on is the Elman network. The Elman
network actually captured what happened
in the hidden layers, but then it copied
it over and made a second copy of it.
And this guy was what was passed on to
the computation at the next time. How
did this matter? So when you were
training, if you were performing back
propagation, you'd back propagate until
here. Copying is not a differentiable
operation. So during training, the
network itself would be sliced up like
this where each of these was treated as
a separate training instance and then
you train the network. That make sense
what I just said that there's this. So
what does this mean? This means that
there is no information flowing back
over time. Now, very often what happens
is that something that happens at this
time doesn't really cause the output to
change. It just keeps going on and on
and on and on and then it trigger
something out here and changes the
output out here. If you began slicing
the network and looking at it one slice
at a time without letting the gradients
propagate backward all the way from here
to here, you would miss the fact that
this output was changed because of
something that happened here. And so the
element network does not give you this.
It was it's it's what is called a
partially recurrent network because
during the back propagation stage
information doesn't flow all the way
back to the beginning of time. That make
sense?
Yes. No. Right. And so this is also true
of the Jordan networks.
So the story so far in
time series analysis models must look at
past inputs along with the current
input. Looking at uh so the clone states
they just so
this hidden state was just copied
and passed to this guy. So during back
propagation this whole this thing was
treated as a standalone network where
this guy had been copied from the hidden
state at the previous time. That answer
your question
I guess so since I see no response.
Okay. All right. So
the story so far in time series analysis
models must look at past inputs along
with the current input. Looking at a
finite hor horizon of the past gives us
a convolutional network. Looking into
the infinite past requires recursion.
Knox networks recurs by feeding back the
output to the input. They may feed back
a finite horizon of outputs. These are
what are called simple recurrent
networks. Jordan networks maintain a
running average of uh outputs in a past
outputs in a memory unit. Elman networks
store the hidden unit values for one
time instant and what they called a
context unit. So they are simple or
partially recurrent because during
learning the current error does not
actually propagate all the way into the
past the error gets blocked at the
memory units in Jordan networks and in
the context units. So in the element
network this was called a context unit
in the Elvin networks the derivatives
didn't flow backwards. So is all of this
clear? Everything this is just the
history.
this clear to everybody?
Okay, I can see like a dozen yeses and I
can move on. Three, four, five.
I get less and less. Okay.
Huh. 11 12. Okay, good. So, that leads
us to our second point.
15 seconds, guys.
Okay,
end the port over here.
What is
the answer to the first question?
Second one,
the first memory neuron models don't
have true recurrence because the
derivatives don't get passed backwards
to the answer to the answer to the
question for why this is blocked in
Jordan networks. That's how it was
designed originally. and they dedicate
neurons specifically to store the past
history.
Let's make things a little more
sophisticated. The so-called state space
model. Those of you who are electrical
engineers over here will recognize this
at once. So in the state space model,
you first define a hidden state for the
model. The hidden state at any time is a
function of the input at that time and
the hidden state at the previous time.
The output at any time is just a
function of the hidden state at any
time. So for this whole thing to work of
course you must define h minus one so
that you can compute h0. So this is also
one either an initial setting which can
be a fixed value or a learned parameter.
Now this is what we'll call a fully
recurrent network or simply a recurrent
neural network. And to see why you have
the rest of the lecture right here is
what the model looks like. It's very
simple. at any time. This there's a
hidden state which takes the hidden
state at the previous time and the
current input
and then this hidden state once computed
is used to compute the output. This
model makes sense to all of you guys.
This one
right? Okay. And so how is this used for
actually processing an input? Like I
said h minus one must be defined. So at
time t=0
the hidden state takes hus1 and the
current input and then produces this
output. At time t= 1 the hidden state
takes the hidden state at t0 and the
current input and produces the output
there and so on. So at each time the
current input and the hidden state at
the previous time are taken to compute
are used to compute the current hidden
state value which is then used to
compute the output. So here you can see
that once again if I have an input over
here and I have no further inputs this
is going to influence the hidden state
over here but this hidden state is going
to keep continuing to influence the
hidden states through time and so
because the outputs are derived from
these hidden states. This one input is
going to continue to influence the
outputs for the rest of time.
This make sense
right? So how do you define the initial
state? We'll get to that. Okay. So uh
various choices you can just call this a
zero or when you use back when you
perform backdrop you can also learn this
guy. Okay.
So this model
so these guys every every column is just
a copy of this original network.
Edward that answer your question
I'm using. Okay. So how do we compute
the current hidden state? We'll see that
right. So I just have a little green box
over here to show the hidden state.
And the hidden state actually can be
pretty complex. It can have many layers.
It can be arbitrarily complex like so.
Right?
If I have a hidden state which is just a
single hidden layer, this is what the
network is going to look like. Again,
all columns are identical and input at
time zero affects outputs forever. But
the hidden state itself is just a single
layer. I can have two layers of hidden
states. If I have two layers of hidden
states, then this H minus one must be
defined for each of these two layers for
this whole network to work. And then
once we set these guys up, given any
input, you can continue to proceed to
compute the output for the rest of time.
And you can have more crazy
architectures like so where at any time
the hidden states can have skip
connections. The only key thing is that
the hidden states at any time are
reading values from the hidden states at
the previous time. And the hidden states
are defined values are defined for time
t= minus one. Right?
And you can have something like this
which is a which is a somewhat more
crazy uh network. Once again this is
recurrent because as a unit the hidden
state at any time is looking at the
hidden state values at the previous time
right
and uh what's the difference between a
direct connection so that's exactly what
this difference was over here if I just
made a copy of this guy out here called
it a context and then treated this whole
thing as a single unit
that's a clone state and then there are
no there's no der there are no
derivatives going back this is a unit
all by itself that answer your question
right
so there's no backdrop beyond the uh
behind the context state in the Jordan
network
so
you can have gaps all these crazy
connections as we just saw why just a
one-step recurrence you can in fact even
have recurrence of for multiple time
steps like so. So you can say that the
hidden state at any time is computed
from the hidden state at the previous
time and also the hidden state two time
steps ago. So this is also fine except
for this to work. Now we have to define
both hus and h minus 2 because at this
time you're going to be reading this hus
2. So long as this these initial values
are defined, you can have deeper uh uh
recurrences within the network.
The most common ones of course however
are just these simple networks which
have a onestep recurrence and again all
columns are identical because basically
it's just the same network being used
again and again uh to perform its
computations. So is all of this clear to
everybody? Everything that we've done so
far clear to everybody?
Right. Okay. So,
here are some examples. Now, typically
in the olden olden textbooks, if you saw
pictures of rec neural networks, this is
what they look like. And the first time
I saw these pictures, it gave me a spin.
It g you know, my head spun like
anything because what does this mean? I
mean, I have this output going right
back in. How on earth is it ever going
to be computing something at the next
time? How is it even computing something
at the current time? because it's going
to keep looping on itself forever. No,
this was just a pictorial
representation. This loop meant that
it's recurren that that this is a
recurrent layer. And so you should not
get confused. This picture really means
that the connection is like this. This
is recurrence. The red loop is
recurrence. So at each t each time this
hidden state is computed from the input
and its own value at the previous time.
So this loop is going over time. That's
the illustration. Don't get confused.
Okay. And so this picture represents
this network where the hidden state at
any time looks at the hidden state at
the previous time. This picture actually
represents this network where the hidden
state has two layers and each layer
looks at its own value at the previous
time. So does this these pictures make
sense to you guys?
Yes. Now
right I get one. Okay. And here's one.
Right. So you can see that the all the
vertical connections occur in every
layer. All these loopy connections
basically just refer to uh
refer to records. So even uh your actual
recurren networks will have many more
layers than two
right
one layer is just too small. I'm just
using one and two layer networks for
illustration. Okay. Uh now
what what are H1? So these are these
these guys are the initial values for
both layers are
they are part of the network design
right does make sense okay why do we use
clip connection these are all as design
choices I was just giving you examples
of different kinds of recurrent networks
so let's look at this recurrent network
to see how the actual computation is per
performed
at each time
the hidden state HT
in this first hidden layer is computed
from the input at that time and the
hidden state at the previous time. So
first you compute an aphine function of
the input and the hidden state at the
previous time. So there's a weight
corresponding to the input.
There's another weight corresponding to
the hidden state at the previous time.
And of course there's a bias because
it's an aphine function. and then you
apply an activation function to it and
that gives you the hidden state at the
current time. Subsequently, the output
is obtained by first computing an aine
function of the hidden state at the
current time and then applying an output
activation to it. So, is this
computation making sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
I see one single thumbs up. That's very
812.
I've become less and less greedy days.
Okay. All right. So, uh
here's another network, right? This has
Okay. There's a distinction I wanted to
make. These are what I call current
weights. Current weights because they
represent weights from other layers at
the same time. This I'm indicating we
have supererscript which has only one
value. This with a superscript 1 one
represents a recurrent weight which says
that the hidden values from the first
layer are connecting to the first layer.
So it's w11 two distinct sets of
weights. One are the current weights the
other are the recurrent weights. They
behave somewhat differently and we'll
see more of that in the coming classes.
So if I have a network of this kind
then here is what I have.
This is literally the inference AI right
at each time the hidden state the first
hidden state is obtained by computing an
aphine function of the input through
this current weight and the hidden state
at the same time at the previous time
through this recurrent weight and then
applying an activation to it. The hidden
state at the next layer H2
is computed from by computing an aine
function of the hidden state in the
first layer through this current weight
and the second layer hidden state at the
previous time through this recurrent
weight and then applying an activation
function to it and then finally the
output itself is computed by applying an
computing an activation function on the
hidden state and applying an output
activation to it. So is this sequence of
steps obvious clear to everybody
the compute over here
right very straightforward nothing
complex and so also if I have something
of this kind
you should be able to write it right the
hidden state of the first time first
layer you just comput a fine function of
the input and the hidden state at at the
previous time these are recurrent
weights the hidden state at the Next
layer you for this you comput an aine
function of both the input the hidden
state at the in the f first layer and
the second layer hidden state at the
previous step and the output you compute
an aine function of the first hidden
layer and the second hidden layer and
then and then apply an output activation
to it. So from the picture you should be
able to write up these equations. This
make sense to everybody?
Yes. No, right. Again, remember that the
values of the hidden states, the initial
values of the hidden states at time
minus one are part of the network
parameters that can be either set to a
preset value like zero or one by design
or learned.
So any questions so far?
Any questions so far? How are the
indices constructed for recurrent
weights? What do you mean by indices?
This is just notation, right? So here
this superscript one represent means
that it's the first hidden layer. This
superscript two means that it's the
second hidden layer. That's all. And the
t means that this is occurring at time
t.
Then answering
so how is the weight decided? How do you
decide weights? Okay. W02. Which one?
uh that is that was just my indication
of going from for this weight
from layer.
Okay, don't get too bogged bogged down
by these indices. Uh the uh idea of how
we that we compute these aphine
functions and then apply an activation
to it is important. So is everything
clear so far?
Okay, everything clear yes. No, guys.
I see one. Yes. Give me a few more
and I'll come. All right. Great. Okay.
So now there are many variants on
recurren neural networks. The simplest
one is one where you have no records at
all. Right? The input is used to compute
a hidden value which is used to compute
an output. Then you have something like
this where an input use is used to
compute a hidden value. there are no
further inputs but then you have a
recurrence over the hidden values which
generate a sequence of outputs. Can you
think of something that uh could
that that this kind of network could be
used for? Any example? Something like
this. What would use a network of this
kind?
Database image captioning. This could be
an image, right? You just provide an
image and it's going to generate a
sequence of words, right?
So if I'm captioning images, this is
what it would look like. Uh here is one.
You gen you you look at a sequence of
inputs and then generate an output at
the very end. An example of something of
this kind. What would that be?
Speech sentiment analysis. Final value
of a stock sent semantic analysis. That
is all of this, right? Not text
generation. We'll get there. Okay. So
here's something. You analyze an entire
sequence of inputs. When you run out of
inputs, you begin generating an entire
sequence of outputs. What would be an
example of this?
Anybody? Translation. You look at all of
the English sentence and then you begin
generating the French sentence. You have
to wait till the end to know what was
what was actually said, right? So text
to speech. Yeah. Now text to speech
maybe you can actually hurry up a bit,
but for translation you definitely
cannot. Uh and then this guy over here
is one where every input generates an
output. Now believe it or not, this is
actually the most generic model. All the
other cases can be viewed as special
cases of this guy where either some
things are ignored or some things have
zero value. Basically the basic model is
that corresponding to every input is the
is an output. So this is the model that
that we will actually be looking at in
the rest of today's lecture in the next
lecture. So this makes sense to you.
This is what we use for the stock market
but it's also a generalized the most
generic model right.
So let's look at this. But first the
story so far the time series analysis
must consider past inputs along with the
current input. It must look into the
infinite past and that requires
recursion. Knox networks achieve this by
feeding back the output to the input.
Simple recurrent networks maintain
separate memory or context units to
retain some information about the past.
But during learning, the current error
does not influence the past. State space
models retain information about the past
through recurrent hidden states. These
are fully recurrent networks. The
initial values of the hidden states are
generally learnable parameters as well.
So because you have this continuous
because an input influences outputs
forever. This means that the current
error can be used to update parameters
in the past. You can learn things about
triggers.
How do you train such a network?
So training is just as before except now
our input is going to be uh you know
standard training you get input sequence
uh input output sequences. So current
error does not influence the past in the
Jordan and Elman networks. In this one
it does. Okay. So uh now
here when you train a recurrent network
your an input instance actually consists
of a sequence of inputs and a desired
sequence of outputs.
So the network itself is going to
compute an actual sequence of outputs.
corresponding to that is going to be a
desired sequence of outputs and you're
going to wiggle the network parameters
to minimize the error between the I
generated and the desired output
sequences. That making sense to
everybody?
Yes. No. Okay.
So
thing to note is that this computation
is just a giant shared parameter neural
network. Basically when I use the same
network over and over again this entire
thing can be thought of as one very deep
network where this guy generates an
output out here for instance right
except that all columns are identical.
So this is a shared parameter network
and so network parameters can be trained
via gradient descent or its variance
using shared parameter gradient descent
rules. Gradient computation requires a
forward pass back propagation and
pooling of gradients for parameter
sharing. So which means that anytime you
get an input which consists training
input which consists of an input
sequence and a desired output sequence.
First you're going to pass the input
through the network to generate the
entire sequence of outputs. What does
that look like?
I'm assuming that the hidden layer
itself the hidden state has many layers.
So I'm going to just for notation I'm
saying the hidden state value and the
zeroth layer is the input. Then you go
through all the hidden layers. Each
hidden layer computes an aphine term
from the
hidden layer at the current time in the
lower layer and the the hidden state in
the current time in the lower layer and
the hidden state in the previous time at
the same layer. So this making sense to
you guys? These two terms this guy is
the h below this guy is the h in the
past. So you compute an aphine term from
these two graphs
and then the hidden state over here
itself is obtained by applying an
activation function to this aphine term.
Typically the activation function is
tanh and we will see why and then
finally for the output layer you compute
an a aine term from the final hidden
state and then apply an activation to a
typically a softness. So the pseudo code
making sense to everybody what we just
did
right
so
okay
again milent here we are going through
all the hidden lay hidden states I'm I'm
calling the hidden state at time zero as
the input then I'm going through all the
layers of the hidden states at each
layer you compute an aphine term from
the hidden state at the lower layer in
the same time and the hidden state in
the same layer at the previous time and
then you apply an activation to it. So
that's what this loop does and then once
you're done the final hidden state is
used to compute the output by first
computing an align term and applying a
softness that answer that clarify things
guys
I'm assuming so right so let me continue
so that's how you compute the forward
pass right so
shirang the network parameters are
shared the input is different right
Now
for computing the gradients you must
pass derivatives backwards. Why
backwards? This entire network can be
thought of as one very deep network.
This guy goes all the way here and
generates an output over here. Right? So
if to compute derivatives you have to
start at the very end and then pass the
derivatives backward through the
computation. In effect you're going to
be passing the derivatives backward
through time. So this is called back
propagation through time. This clear to
you guys why the derivatives must be
computed in this manner.
Right? And so
to simplify to the illustration I'm
going to change the figure like instead
of showing this horizontal arrow coming
out of the side of the box I'm going to
show this loopy arrow to just to clarify
that whatever is being output from here
is both going up and coming in here.
This is only for illustration and we're
going to use uh this network is going to
generate an output an output sequence.
There's a desired output sequence. We
compute the divergence between the
desired output sequence and the actual
output sequence. We are not computing
the divergences between individual
outputs and individual desired outputs.
No, that's not what we do. the the
divergence is between the desired
sequence and the actual sequence. And
you can see the difference over here.
For example, if you were doing machine
translation, the network may generate an
output of 10 words, but the desired
output may have six words. You don't
have a onetoone correspondence, but you
do have an error between the two, right?
So the divergence is actually between
two sequences not between two
not between individual outputs and their
and their corresponding entries in the
desired output. That make sense to you
guys that this is actually a divergence
between two sequences. Yes or no?
Right. Okay. So and this causes all
kinds of problems.
For example, if I'm performing machine
translation, the network goes out and
produces a 100word output. Garbage and
the desired output is 10 words. How do
you compute a divergence between a
10word output and a 100word output? It's
not very clear, right? Because something
that's very important is for us to be
able to compute the derivative of the
divergence with respect to all of these
guys. And that's a challenge. We'll get
to that, but first some notation. Okay,
in my illustration, I'm going to use
only one hidden state. So the hidden
state value is called H of T. Of course,
the hidden state is computed from an
aphine term. So the aine term has a
superscript one to show that it's the
first aine term. The output is also
computed from an aphine term which is
computed obtained from h. So this is the
second aine term. So it has a
superscript 2. So h of t is a function
of is computed by applying an activation
to z1 of t. z1 of t is obtained from the
input in the hidden state at the
previous time. Y of t is computed by
applying an activation to z2 of t and z2
of t is an as an aine function of just h
of t. This clear to everybody?
Yes. now.
Okay. So, I'm going to use this as my
illustration. Okay.
And I have weights. So, w superscript 1
represent the represents the weights
here. W superscript 2 represents the
weights here. W superscript 1 represents
these recurrent weights. These are the
guys we need to learn, right? So, and
then of course we have the divergence,
right? The divergence is actually a
function of two sequences.
The first step of backdrop is for us to
compute the derivative of the divergence
with respect to this y of t. In fact, we
need the derivative of the divergence
with respect to all of these y's. But
when you compute the derivatives, the
divergence between two sequences where
you don't have any kind of onetoone
correspondence like if the network
generates 100 words and the desired
output is only 10 words, there's no one
to correspondence. So how do you decide
determine how perturbing this a little
bit changes the divergence? It ends up
being a challenge, right? So uh we sort
of tend to take some make some take some
shortcuts and simplify matters to deal
with this. We'll get to that. For the
back prop rules, we are going to use two
basic uh repeatedly use two basic rules.
The first is this guy. If I have an
influence diagram of this kind where I
have y I - 1 influencing zi which
influences y i which influences the loss
l. Then initially I would have the
derivative of the loss with respect to
yi. That's this guy right?
Then to compute the derivative of the
loss with respect to zi,
all I need to do is to multiply right
multiply the derivative of the of the
loss with respect to yi by the
derivative of yi with respect to zi.
Do you guys remember this rule?
Yes. No.
Right. Then to compute the derivative of
the loss with respect to yi minus one, I
need to simply multiply the derivative
of y the loss with respect to zi by the
derivative of zi with respect to y i - 1
which is just w.
So derivative with respect to yi minus
one is derivative with respect to zi *
w. Do you guys remember this rule?
Yes. No.
Okay. I'm seeing like three yes S's.
Maybe I can get a few more on the right
hand side. The thumbs ups are missing.
Come on, guys. Five. That's sad. Okay,
then finally, what is the derivative
with respect to W? Do you remember this?
The derivative with respect to W was
simply Yi -1
times the derivative of L with respect
to Z.
Right? You remember this guys?
Right. So
we're going to use these three rules
again and again. Okay. The other rule
we're going to use is that if I have yi
influencing zi and zi + 1 and both of
them influence l, the derivative of
respect l with respect to i is going to
be the derivative of l with respect to
zi time w1
plus the derivative of l with respect to
zius 1 * w2.
This this clear to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. So then the rest is easy. Okay.
Here's what we will do. The first thing
we do, we somehow assume that we can
manipulate our divergence so that there
is actually a onetoone correspondence
between the divergence between the
desired outputs and the actual outputs.
If you can manipulate it in that manner,
then the derivative of the overall
divergence with respect to any yt just
collapses to the derivative of the
divergence between the desired output at
time t and the actual output at time t
with respect to yt. That make sense?
We're going to manipulate our divergence
so that there's a onetoone
correspondence. And then I can I can
just look at this local match of the
desired output at this time and the
actual output at this time. I compute a
divergence from it and then I can get a
derivative of that divergence with
respect to yt. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. And so I'm going to assume that I
now have the derivative of the overall
divergence with respect to each of these
y's because that's simply going to be
the derivative of the local divergence
with respect to the corresponding y if
we have manipulated things carefully.
Okay.
And then so when I perform back
propagation through time at the very
first time I'm going to assume that I
have the derivative of the divergence
with respect to yt.
Okay because that's how we define the
divergence.
And then once I have this how do I
compute the derivative of the divergence
with respect to the z if I have the
derivative with respect to yt? How do I
do that guys?
Anybody? How do I do that?
Normal backdrop. What is the normal
backdrop rule?
Multiply by right multiply by the
Jacobian of this activation. Right? Yes
or no?
Okay. And so that's what we're going to
do, right? We're going to multiply this
derivative with respect to Y by the
derivative of Y with respect to Z, which
is simply the Jacobian of the
activation. That's easy. So, we got the
derivative out here. Next, I want the
derivative with respect to this guy,
which is h of t. What is the derivative
of with respect of of the divergence
with respect to h of t? What will it be?
Anybody? What's it going to be?
What will it be guys?
Come on, that's easy.
Okay. Okay. Give me a thumbs up if you
have given up.
Multiply by the weight, right? So that's
it. So all you have to do is multiply by
this weight and you get the derivative
with respect to h. Correct?
again.
So you you have to write multiply by the
weight since we're using the column
notation. And now what is the derivative
with respect to this weight? What was
the derivative with respect to this
weight?
Do you remember this? What was that?
What was it guys?
That is simply going to be this age
times the derivative with respect to the
Z. Correct?
Yes or no?
That's this rule we That's this rule
here. This guy. That's all we're using,
right? I'm literally just plugging in
these rules. And so if I want the
derivative with respect to this weight,
it's this h of t times the derivative
with respect to z, this z. This clear to
everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay, then what is the derivative out
here? What is the derivative out here?
What's it going to be?
Give me your 5 seconds before I answer.
So, what's the derivative out here?
Okay, your 5 seconds are up. Come on,
guys. It's going to be simply right
multiplying the derivative over here by
the Jacobian of this activation.
Correct?
Yes or no?
Right. So here we have it. The
derivative out here is going to be the
derivative at h right multiplied by the
derivative of the activation.
What is the derivative
out here? Actually this we don't need
but what is the derivative with respect
to this weight? What would that be?
Again
using the same rules as before it's
going to be x times the derivative of
the loss with respect to h. Correct?
I'm speaking of the derivative for the
weight.
Okay.
And then what is the derivative for this
weight?
What is the derivative for this weight?
Anybody? What is the derivative for this
weight?
It's going to be this h
times the derivative with respect to
this z. Correct?
Yes or no?
Can I see like 10 yeses? So, I know at
least 5% of the class got it.
Okay,
I think I'm doing slightly better than
five 5%. So, that's good. Okay.
And so, the derivative with respect to
this weight is simply xt * the
derivative with respect to z1. And the
derivative with respect to this weight
is simply going to be htus one time the
derivative with respect to z1 over here.
So is everybody good with this set of
equations so far? Because now things get
slightly more wonky. Is everybody good?
Can I see like 10 yeses? Okay, 15. I'm
getting greedy.
Thumbs ups, right? 15 thumbs ups.
Okay. 11
11 12 Oh my god. Okay, thank you. So
now we are going to take a step back. We
have we have we are finished with this
time instant. What we going to do is to
go next to this time instant because
we're going backwards through time. And
so the first thing I'm going to assume
that I have the derivative with respect
to yt minus one. So I can get the
derivative out here by simply
multiplying the derivative with respect
at yt with respect to yt minus one by
the jacobian of this activation.
Correct? Yes or no?
Just a simple yes or no. Okay, good. So
what next?
Next I want to compute the derivative
with respect to this guy. But if I want
to compute the derivative with respect
to this htus one, htus one influences
the divergence in two ways. One is like
so the other is like so right? Yes or
no?
And so I must if I want the derivative
of the divergence with respect to htus
one that's going to be the derivative
with respect to z at time t -1 times
this w
plus the derivative
with respect to z1 over here times this
w
that make sense to everybody
can I see like tiny asses this.
Yeah. Okay, perfect. Right. So, that was
easy. Now, things get a little crazy.
If I want the derivative with respect to
the weight out here, the derivative with
respect to the weight out here is simply
this hidden state times the derivative
with respect to the Z. Correct?
Yes or no?
But then this weight was the same as
this weight. Correct?
These two were the same weight.
They are a shared parameter network. So
which means that whatever derivative I
computed over here, I'm going to be
adding this term to what I already have,
I have a plus equals. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. Huh?
Right. And so
great. Same thing. If I want the
derivative for this weight,
okay, if I want a derivative for the Z,
the derivative for this Z is simply
obtained by multiplying the derivative
for this H with respect to the Jacobian
of this unit as before.
And then I want a derivative for this
weight. But this weight is the same as
this guy. And so I'm actually going to
get a plus equal to which is say to say
this x times the derivative at this z
this guy but I already computed one such
term from here so it's actually going to
get added into it
make sense to everybody
yes no
okay two s's I'll take two okay what
about this guy now will it have is it
going to be standalone or is it going to
be an increment
for this one.
Remember this weight is the same as this
weight. Correct?
It's going to be an increment. And so
when I compute the derivative for this
weight, it's going to be it's going to
be h the h over here multiplied by the
derivative over here. But that term
actually adds to what I already
previously computed. And so I've shown
you the computation of derivatives
through two time steps, but then the
rest of them follow the same rule. I can
spin it all the way back and then
eventually I can even compute the
derivative with respect to h minus one
which can be a learned parameter. So did
this make sense? This whole thing makes
sense to you guys? Yes or no?
Right. So I have the entire set of the
pseudo code for the all the operations
out here.
You assume that you have the derivative
of the divergence with respect to all
the y's. You start at the end and then
go backward through time. At each time
you first compute the derivative with
respect to z, then if this guy has been
if the derivative with respect to this
weight has been initialized to zero, you
just increment it by this h times the
derivative with respect to z. Then you
compute the derivative with respect to
this this guy by actually the derivative
with respect to this h is going to be a
sum over two terms one going up and one
down. So over here the future is zero
right and then uh the derivatives for
the weights are always incremented
basically
I get myself confused the pseudo codes
here okay
and I have uh code for this too
so besides a little bit of confusion at
the very end did all of this make sense
okay and so you can just generalize this
to any odd architecture
So now
we have P Okay.
15 seconds, guys.
Let me at this point.
What's the answer to the first question?
True or false?
False. Okay. And second one,
option two. Let's see.
You don't update the network after each
input. You update the network after the
entire sequence. And the divergence is
the divergence between the actual
sequence of the outputs and the desired
sequence of outputs. This cannot always
be decomposed into the sum of
divergences at individual times. So we
have to manipulate things in order to
get something that's convenient. Okay,
so far so good. Now let's jump forward.
Right, in all the stuff that we've seen
so far, we've assumed that I'm computing
things left to right that the input is
coming in sequentially.
But there are many cases where you get
the entire input sequence and then you
are supposed to make predictions about
intermediate values. For example, if I'm
doing part of speech uh tagging. So part
of speech tagging, you will get the
entire sentence, you know, I whatever
saw
a
light. Okay.
And then you're going to be asked what
is the part of speech of this guy? What
is the part of this speech of this guy?
Right? In these cases, you have the
entire sequence. It doesn't make sense
to only look at it left to right.
For example, if I just saw I saw a light
and stopped right here, it would seem to
me that this guy is a noun, right? But
if I saw if the next word was box, then
light is obviously describing the word
box. So then it becomes obvious that
this is an adjective. So looking into
the future changed my opinion about this
word. It helps to look about look into
the future. Make sense to everybody?
Yes. Now,
right. So, whenever the future is
available, if the present influences the
future, the future informs about the
past. So, you would like to use the
future. But then, can I use a network of
this kind where the recurrence is this
guy informs this guy and then this guy
informs this guy right back? Can I use a
network of this kind?
No, it's just going to be endless
looping, right? How do you resolve this?
That's what birectional neal networks
are about. Birectional networks
introduced originally by Paliwal and uh
uh I forget who uh Shuster and Paliwal
back in 97. Brilliant idea. It took took
people a very long time to recognize the
importance of it. Here's what you do.
you split the forward and backwards.
So within any layer you have a forward
network. So the the layer gets these
inputs. These inputs go into
like so into the forward network and the
forward network which has an hus one
defined analyzes the input from the
front to the back. Within the same layer
you have a backward network which looks
at the same guys but then it analyzes it
from back to the front backwards. This
is not back prop over the forward
network. They're two independent
networks. This is analyzing it front to
back. That's analyzing it back to front.
Each of them generates an output.
You combine these two outputs out here
typically by concatenating. So you know
you have the h from the forward and the
h from the backward. to concatenate the
two and that's going to be the output of
the overall layer the block. This making
sense to everybody
and how this prevents the looping
all of you guys. Okay. Can I get 10? I
agree. I'm greedy. 15 yeses
not like three four 6 8 10.
Okay. That's 15. Thank you. So the
forward net is going to process the
input from time zero to time t only
computing the hidden state values and
then the backward net computes things
only from the backwards to the beginning
and the final thing combines the two
outputs typically by concatenation.
Mana did that answer your question?
Yes ma'am
assuming it did. Okay. So
this is one layer and you can connect
them in any in fact within the layer
itself this could these could be
multi-layer things like so but typically
this is more the standard structure
within each layer you have a forward net
and a backward net and you can stack
many of them up. So uh this is how you
would have a birectional network and not
all layers need to be biirectional. You
could have a unidirectional layer
anywhere in between although it kind of
breaks the principle of looking into the
future.
So this is our final point.
So 15 seconds guys. Edward
depends on the problem right
as this poll tells you.
Okay, I'll end the poll because I think
everybody's answered.
So, what is the answer guys? False.
Right. In stock in the stock market, you
don't have access to the future. So,
it's going to be unidirectional. But if
I'm doing uh part of speech tagging, I
have entire sentences. I need to know
the tag for a word in the middle. I have
the access to the future. So, it depends
on the problem, right? And so this is
false. I have some code over here. Let's
skip the code. But let's skip to the
more important bit. The point about the
code over here is that the forward and
backward nets will use the same code.
You just pass the data in in reverse,
right? How do you do back propagation?
So in the forward, the backward net
computed HB. Sorry, HB. The forward net
computed HF.
And then over here you concatenate
concatenated the two HF HB
to get the output of the layer. Right?
So now when you're performing back
propagation you can assume that you got
the derivative with respect to the h
which is to say that you have got the
derivative the derivative with respect
to the h is going to have these many
components. The first half is going to
represent the derivative with respect to
the forward the forward values. The
second half is going to represent the
derivatives with respect to the backward
values. That make sense to everybody?
Then if I compute the derivative with
respect to h, I'm also getting the
derivative with respect to the forward
and the backward values. So now I can
pass this forward value guys
down to here.
And so now I have the derivative of the
divergence with respect to the outputs
of these boxes.
I can pass the backward value guys out
down to here. And so I have the
derivatives of the divergence with
respect to the outputs of these boxes
from these guys. And now and and then
for the forward guys I can just use back
propagation going back to front and
that's going to compute the derivatives
for all the parameters in the forward
net. It's also going to compute the
derivative with respect to the inputs
which is to say with respect to x these
axis the forward back propagation
through the forward net is going to give
you derivatives for all the weights in
the forward net and with respect to
these axis
in the backward net back propagation
because computation went from the end to
the beginning back prop is now going to
go from the beginning to the end And
that back propagation is going to give
you derivatives with respect to all the
parameters of the network. But that too
is going to give you a derivative with
respect to all of these axis.
That makes sense to everybody,
right?
This make sense to everybody? Yes. No.
So okay, I'll answer once this is done.
understand and then finally because I
got a derivative with respect to x from
both the forward and the backward net
and x is going into both of them. So the
actual derivative with respect to the
input to the layer is going to be the
sum of the derivatives obtained from
obtained from the forward and
backward. So Bruno in the actual code
you would flip the input and pass it.
Now these two are two different sets of
parameters. So you would actually if you
actually look at my pseudo code over
here what you will see is that I have an
RNN forward and then for the
biirectional you just flip the input and
just use reuse the same code
that's exactly what you do
right and so you don't need to write two
codes write the code twice you just need
to know which parameters to pass.
So, did all of this
make sense, too?
That's right. Sure. So, did all of this
make sense so far?
And so, I have pseudo code for it, but I
skip it. Okay. And so, we get to the end
of that.
So, time series analysis must consider
past inputs along with current input.
Recurrent networks look into the
infinite past through a state space
framework. hidden states that recurs on
themselves.
So training recurrent networks requires
defining a divergence between the actual
and desired output sequences.
Back propagating gradients over the
entire chain of which requires back
propagating gradients over the entire
chain of recursion in the opposite
direction of computation which for a
standard recussion is from the end to
the beginning backwards through time and
then you pull gradients with respect to
the individual parameters over time
because you use the same parameters
repeatedly across time. Now birectional
networks analyze data both ways
beginning to end and end to beginning to
make predictions. In these networks,
back prop must follow the chain of
recursion and gradient pooling
separately in the forward and reverse
networks.
So that's the end of today's lecture.
RNNs, they're great models for time
series analysis, time series prediction,
time series classification, sequence
generation, but the simple model that we
just saw has some challenges. And we'll
see this look at the challenges and how
we solve them in the next class. So uh
is there
did the lecture make sense to all of you
guys? Do you have any questions?
Give me a thumbs up if the lecture made
sense. If you have any questions, now's
your time to ask or I'll stop the
recording.
No questions.
Okay,
>> there is a question.
>> Okay. What is it?
>> Yeah, I was asking how do we use the
future information to predict to make
prediction since it is just concatenated
with the past and present information.
>> Okay. So, so just take a look. Suppose I
say I saw
a sorry
let's say
I bought
a light as an
shoot right
so if I want to perform
part of speech tagging. This would be C
I bought
a there's going to be something here,
right? Light shoe,
right?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Okay. So now this guy is going to
process shoe first and that's going to
influence my decision for light and it
goes backward. This guy is going to
process I first and then it's going to
go forward through time.
So by the time you come here, this guy
has told you what the past words, what
evidence the past words have brought.
This guy has told you what evidence the
future words have brought. And those two
are combined into the stage.
That answer your question.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
Let me stop the recording.
>> Yeah. I have a question.